Inventory of the Jerdone Family Papers 1753-1890, 1771-1845
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Correspondence, 1753-1890. (Box 1-10)
  - Letters, 1820-1829., 65 items. (Box 6-7)
    - Letters, 1824., 13 items. (Box-folder 6:6)
      - I[sabella] Mitchell, n.p. to her brother, Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 12 November 1824., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:6)
        Discusses health; complains about overseers; reports Charles Thompson has found a new overseer for following year; relates a chair bought for her to ride around the plantation; reports on crops; other family news.
      - I[sabella] Mitchell, n.p. to her brother, Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 19 December 1824., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:6)
        Discusses health; reports son George will go back to Hampden-Sydney; "He returns to Hampden-Sydney the 1 of July, he had a trip there about ten days ago, they have an entire set of new teachers so he agreed to go back. I had much rather he was there than at this university there is not the same temptation for extravagance"; reports news of Do[c]t[o]r Honyman's poor condition; other family news.
    - Letters, 1825., 11 items. (Box-folder 6:7)
      - I[sabella] Mitchell, n.p. to her brother, Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 25 January 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Discusses health; reports Sally Thompson's children are very ill; reports George began class; has not heard from the Doct[o]r; reports overseer seems to be industrious; complains of neighbors stealing her livestock; other family news.
      - Edward Walkins, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 15 March 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Reports no new cases of small pox; discusses material necessary for "netting the sain [seine]"; gives idea of cost to make netting; discusses crops and weather; reports many newborn children, lambs, and calves.
      - I[sabella] Mitchell, n.p. to her brother, Francis Jerdone, [Louisa County, Virginia], 25 March 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Discusses health, reports wet weather has delayed planting; complains of slaves stealing her livestock and goods; refers to hired out slave who ran away; other family news.
      - Edward Watkins, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 7 April 1825., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Believes need new cotton machine; discusses health of slaves; reports has finished seine but it is too short; refers to bad conduct of son's servant; discusses running away of three slaves; complains of ungratefulness; family news; P.S. slaves have returned; promises to be more strict with them as they have become spoiled.
      - R[ich]m[on]d Lewis, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 8 April [18]25., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Informs there is little hope for sister's [Isabella Jerdone Mitchell] recovery.
      - Nat Thompson, Pottiesville, [Louisa County, Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 14 April 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Hopes to share fences at the plantation until next fall because Jerdone's are in such bad condition and he won't be able to fix them during this season.
      - S[ally] I. Thompson, n.p. to her uncle, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 9 June 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Writes to announce and arrange funeral service for her "mother"; describes intended service and expresses respect for strength of her "mother."
      - Edward Watkins, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, [Louisa County, Virginia], 15 June 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Writes to explain he expects corn prices to rise; discusses severe weather of past week; relates other business.
      - M. Middleton, n.p. to his cousin, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 18 July 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Reports death of Virginia Thompson; reports illness of cousin Garland [Thompson]; requests for body of child to be interred by grave of the Mitchell's child; reports also illness of George Mitchell at Hampden-Sydney.
      - Edward Watkins, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 2 October 1825., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Has wanted to write until corn was beaten and wheat cleaned and measured; reports had waited to get the cotton machines in Richmond because of illness of overseer and son but went recently; didn't receive it as appearance too small; other family news, business and reference to health of the "Black People."
      - Garland Thompson, Hanover County, [Virginia] to his Uncle, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 7 December 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 6:7)
        Sends tombstones for aunt Isabella [Jerdone] Mitchell and for his [Garland Thompson] daughter; includes 7 instructions of how stones should be placed.
    - Edward Watkins, Providence Forge to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 24 January 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Apologizes for not following Jerdone's wishes with the hogs; discusses progress in sale of crops; requests a few more horses to tend the crops better; refers to improvements in farm system; reports on illness in the area.
    - Edward Watkins, Providence Forge, to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 14 March 1826., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Discusses crops and prices; hopes to begin fishing soon; refers to fondness of "the [Black] People" to run away and reports some instances; gives count of livestock and tells of loss of mule; reports work done on land and repair of fences; discusses health in area.
    - Edward Watkins, "Providence Forge," [New Kent County, Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 25 May 1826., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Reports on weather and development of crops; refers to health of "the People" [slaves] as in "better health."
    - Francis Jerdone, n.p. to James Innes, n.p., 1827., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Reports death of George Braikenridge and his [Francis Jerdone] youngest son, James; refers to weather and other business concerns.
      Including ALS from Francis Jerdone, n.p. to his nephew, George Weare Braikenridge, n.p., 1827, concerning account of entire Jerdone family and their doings. 3 pages. Including ALS from Francis Jerdone, n.p. to Garland Thompson, n.p., 18 September 1827, concerning bond of mortgage held by his [Garland Thompson] father that he [Francis Jerdone] would like to settle. 1 page.
    - Edward Watkins, Providence Forge to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 26 January 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Discusses crops and the effects of the past weather on them; discusses clearing of land for future corn crops; refers to illness of the slaves, the people suffer much for want of blankets, in severe instances we have been compelled to furnish them ourselves when sick or they would have suffered very much; reports illness of Mrs. Watkins.
    - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 15 March 1827., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Discusses improvements done on the estate, especially on the field called "hell swamp"; reports on planting, amount of crops and sales; refers to possibility of a Dr. Morris summoning Mr. Jerdone as to why there is no public road through his tract of land.
    - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 3 May 1827., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Refers to amount lost during drought the previous year; hopes to make estate more profitable through his management; reports on improvements of estate; discusses sale of crops and prices; discusses weather and water supply; discusses health of the [Black] People.
    - George Weare Braikenridge, Broomwell House, Brislington near Bristol, [England] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 29 May 1827., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Writes of father's [George Braikenridge] death on January 6, 1827; writes of his father's life; reports on family news; discusses health and business.
    - Tho[ma]s Ritchie, n.p. to Francis Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, [Virginia], 17 November 1827., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Complains of bad quality of corn; requests he take back the remaining 200 bushels.
    - Joan D. Thomson, Jedburgh, [Scotland] to her cousin, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, Virginia, 10 March 1828., 2 pages. XCy of ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Discusses health; discusses changes in town buildings; gives town news; asks for news of the family in Virginia; discusses weather.
    - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa County, Virginia, 28 June 1828., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Discusses wheat crop and estimates grain expected; gives report of progress of crops; describes goods sent; refers to health of "the [Black] People."
    - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Wallers Tavern, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia], 1 May 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Describes work done in the fields and improvements of the estate; discusses planting of crops and weather; refers to the neighbors' crops; discusses health of the slaves.
    - [Edward Watkins], Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 4 July 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Has sent two barrels of fish; reports on quality of the crops; discusses weather; reports illness among slaves; gives family news.
    - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to Francis Jerdone, Wallers Tavern, Spotsylvania County, Virginia, 20 July 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Expresses pleasure in prospect of Jerdone visiting; refers to progress of crops and weather; reports on rumors of slaves uprising; refers to many in jail in Norfolk, Gloucester, and Williamsburg; hopes to visit Jerdone in August; discusses health.
    - John Jerdone, Spotsylvania County, [Virginia] to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 21 November 1829., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:1)
      Discusses crops and planting; refers to letter from John Lewis; refers to interests in digging gold; doubts the opinions on finding gold.
  - Letters, 1830-1839., 246 items. (Box-folder 7-9)
    - Letters, 1830. (Box-folder 7:2-3)
      - J[ohn] Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa County, [Virginia], 1 January 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Refers to painful boils; reports forced to wait to slaughter hogs because of weather; reports roads poor for visit; refers to crops and harvesting.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 4 January 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports on progress of wheel repairing; reports accident Barbara had which cut her left eye; refers to misconduct of slave "Minny"; other family news.
      - J[ohn] Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 7 January 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Discusses weather and killing hogs; reports sent hogs for Stubbs allowance; refers to bother by people fox hunting.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 8 January 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Refers to injury of Barbara's eye; refers to poor business lately; hopes to visit soon; refers to run-away slave.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 24 January 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports on health of slaves and family; refers to weather in terms of crops; reports marriage of two slaves if no objections come from the rest of the family.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 29 January 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports sending cornmeal and hominy; reports filling ice house; refers to health and bad weather; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 12 February 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports progress on carriage body; reports new mill shaft ready to be put in; refers to bad weather and delay in ploughing [sic].
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 21 February 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports new mill shaft in and working; reports good weather and condition of crops; asks for $100 for clothes and a "phial of ink"; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 26 February 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports ploughing [sic] going well and wheat has mended from frost; returns knife; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 4 March 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Refers to grinding of wheat and corn; apologizes that wheat isn't done but explains it would have required stopping work on dam; refers to water rising; reports that dam work is first priority and cotton will be ginned when dam is finished; hopes weather will continue to be good as he has not begun planting.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 7 March 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Offers to fix wheelbarrow; refers to not going to court[house] following day; reports a F lock of swans which flew over his house; other family news.
      - J[ohn] Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 8 March 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Refers to death of Aunt [Elizabeth Jerdone] Macaulay; refers to plowing and progress of crops; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 11 March 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Acknowledges receipt of goods; reports sowing plant patches of vegetables and tobacco; discusses weather and crops.
      - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 11 March 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Discusses letter sent to John [Jerdone]; reports crops and progress in ploughing; refers to illness of the [Black] People.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 14 March 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports fine weather and progress of crops; reports repaired wheelbarrow; refers to mill running well with new shaft; requests cloves and seeds for radishes and lettuce.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 26 March 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports on weather; reports on sending wheelbarrow as well as other things; reports on crops; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 28 March 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Refers to rising of river and damage done to property; refers to "syd" who has been wandering between plantations; reports crops p1anted; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p., to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 30 March 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:2)
        Reports return of Syd to the plantation; refers to his not whipping him; reports of sowing conditions for the oats; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 1 April 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports working on the road; is not in favor of removing Watkins; reports high waters in the river; refers to sowing oats; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 3 April 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports weather conditions and effects on crops: refers to preacher's visit for dinner as well as Jno. Bronaugh; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 18 April 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports on plowing and planting progress; requests $100; inquires after [his brother] Frank; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 29 April 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports damage done to the dam; reports recommencement of both grinding and sowing; refers to the return of the "gold-hunters" but hasn't heard their success rate.
      - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 21 May 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses wife's illness for which he brought her to Williamsburg to see Dr. Gault [Galt]; refers to illness of the "Black People"; discusses crops and prices; 2 refers to fishing.
      - W[illia]m Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia] to Edward Watkins, "Providence Forge," New Kent [County, Virginia], 4 June 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports on weather; refers to lagging tobacco prices; refers to attraction of gold mines; other family news.
      - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 15 June 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses wife's poor health and Dr. Gault's [Gait] low opinion of her recovery; discusses slaves' illness as well; reports on progress of crops and weather.
      - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 4 August 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses wife's health and plans to take her "up the country"; discusses harvesting, crops, and business; refers to anticipated visit.
      - William Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia] to Edward Watkins, "P[rovidence] Forge," New Kent [County, Virginia], 3 September 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Refers to illness of Mrs. Watkins; reports on weather and crops; expresses father's opinion on travel; refers to delivery of crops and preparations; other family news.
      - J[ohn] Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 9 September 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses health; refers to rain and rise of water; reports this not sufficient to start grinding; reports on condition of carriage and lists some repairs needed.
      - Edward Watkins, Prov[idence] Forge, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 20 September 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses health of himself and slaves; reports wife's death and when funeral will be preached; discusses crops and expected prices; suggests waiting to sell corn until following year to get better price.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 26 September 1830., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Refers to rising of river and damage done; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 29 September 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Has gotten roads passable again; late frost has done no injury to dam; grinding and sawing again; gold hunters.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 8 October 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Refers to ill health; reports on weather and crop development.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa County, [Virginia], 11 October 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Thanks father for the veal; reports runaway has returned and received a "remembrance for his past conduct"; reports wet weather preventing ploughing the low ground.
      - Edward Watkins, Providence Forge, [Virginia] to William Jerdone, Pottiesville, Louisa County, Virginia, 19 October 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses unfavorable wet weather for ploughing the low lands; discusses crops and suggests waiting to sell corn until following year; advises to sell wheat as soon as possible; refers to tolerable health of the servants but fears a sickly fall.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 3 November 1830., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses going ashore of boat shipping goods and damage of goods; thankful not to have lost all goods; refers to change in weather.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 6 November 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports on sale of wheat by [brother] William; refers to enclosure of William's letter.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 9 November 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports receipt of turkeys and lead; refers to [brothers] Frank and William's sale of wheat; other family news.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa [County, Virginia], 15 November 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports receipt of goods; refers to William's letter; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 29 November 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Has sent bags of feathers and jug for vinegar; reports water has done no damage to the mill except some swelling of the machinery; refers to visit of next day.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 13 December 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Reports safe receipt of goods and servants; promises to send servants back to assist with hogs; reports plan to go to Louisa Court following day.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa County, [Virginia], 17 December 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses weather; requests to know when servants are needed for hogs; reports has slaughtered his hogs and were tolerably well.
      - Jno. Jerdone. n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 18 December 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Refers to visit with family at Mrs. Smith's; expresses disappointment that [brothers] Frank and William had not returned; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 25 December 1830., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:3)
        Discusses weather; reports marriage of son of Captain John Graves; refers to prolonged absence of [brothers] W[illia]m and Frank; refers to Dr. Macaulay's gold fever; other family news.
    - Letters, 1831., 44 items. (Box-folder 7:4-6)
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 2 January 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:4)
        Glad to hear [brothers] Frank and W[illia]m are home; reports John Bronaugh has left for Abbingdon [Abington, Virginia?] through Richmond to engage in the mercantile line; reports has stopped grinding because of rain.
      - Jno. Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone, Louisa County, [Virginia], 14 January 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:4)
        Reports sale of oats; refers to weather and roads preventing travel; refers to wheels repaired and ready to be sent; other family news.
      - John Jerdone, n.p. to his father, Francis Jerdone sen[io]r, Louisa [County, Virginia], 15 January 1831., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 7:4)